# Avaya Kumar Baniya

Curious and motivated Software Developer with 4 years of hands-on experience designing and developing large and small scale applications. Well-versed in multiple coding languages and software design patterns and highly enthusiastic about research regarding software development and technology as a whole.

Contact: (+1) 757-980-9675 Email: baniyaavaya@gmail.com Address: Norfolk, Virginia

#### **EDUCATION**

#### **Old Dominion University,** Norfolk, USA — M.S in Computing

August 2023 - Present

### **Islington College**, Nepal — B.Sc. (Hons) in Computing

Affiliated with London Metropolitan University

October 2016 - October 2019

#### **EXPERIENCE**

## **Silk Innovation**, Lalitpur, Nepal — Head of Software Development February 2021 - July 2023

- Led the software architecture design and development of multiple online wallet systems (<u>SajiloPay</u>, <u>Icash</u>) which comprised of api development, system administration portal development, while communicating with various service providers to integrate their services into our system
- Implemented and managed the conversion of an in-production monolith application into multiple microservices, using HTTP and message brokers to communicate between them inside docker containers
- Mentored new software developers and interns regarding the development process of the company, while assigning and assisting them with their tasks
- Provide technical customer support to clients
- Development of domain specific packages using laravel and spring boot: "contact-mail" that can send contact us emails from a website to multiple emails and "compare-microservice-and-vendor" that preconfigures the boilerplate code with the feature to check transaction status between vendor through api and microservice through database
- Managed the full lifecycle of software development, from planning to deployment and maintenance, while participating in code review meetings, identifying bugs, inefficiencies and potential solutions to emergent issues

#### **Silk Innovation**, Lalitpur, Nepal— Software Developer

October 2019 - January 2021

- Developed and managed website updates using laravel, javascript and django to align with customer needs
- Presented project updates to customers to gather feedback and assess satisfaction
- Enhance performance and add new features to existing software systems

#### **LANGUAGES**

Java, python, php, JavaScript, MySQL, C /

#### **SKILLS**

Git, Spring Boot, Laravel, Django, React, Express, Node.js, Android Studio, Jupyter, docker, RDMS, Object-Oriented Software Design, Agile Methodologies, CI/CD, Web Development, Api development, GitHub, GitLab, Jira project management

#### **TOP SIDE PROJECTS**

#### **Water Tester App –** Full Stack Engineer

Build a prototype android application using java that could scan a special type of litmus paper to estimate water purity using k-nearest neighbors machine learning algorithm. The app won the 'Code for a Cause Impact Prize' on Nepal Hackathon 2018 organized by AngleHack

#### **Job Portal** – Full Stack Engineer

- Used Laravel, JavaScript, and Mysql to build a multi vendor job portal web application.
- Integrated real time notification feature using Socket.IO and javascript.

#### Job classification with AI

 Employed a variety of classification algorithms to classify new job postings based on their descriptions and categorize them to the class or industry that each job post belongs to.